<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>reading on Harshad Saykhedkar</title>
    <link>https://harshadss.github.io/tags/reading/</link>
    <description>Recent content in reading on Harshad Saykhedkar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright @ Harshad Saykhedkar</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://harshadss.github.io/tags/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Readings in Human Body, Evolution and Biology</title>
      <link>https://harshadss.github.io/posts/studying_body_biology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://harshadss.github.io/posts/studying_body_biology/</guid>
      <description>Throughout my school life I tried to stay away from biology studies. I specifically chose studying physics and maths instead of biology in higher secondary school. Even during secondary school, science 1 generally had physics and chemistry whereas science 2 contained protozoans and all other wiggling beasts. Guess who barely got over line in science 2.
The logic for a high school students in India was simple. You chose biology if you wanted to be a doctor (or do a research in microbiology) which meant spending many years studying and daddy needs to have lot of money to get you into medical school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheklist Manifesto &amp; Thinking Fast and Slow</title>
      <link>https://harshadss.github.io/posts/cheklist_manifesto_ruminations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://harshadss.github.io/posts/cheklist_manifesto_ruminations/</guid>
      <description>I read ‘the checklist manifesto’ by Atul Gawande. I am a firm believer in books and advice in general from anyone in practice oriented profession: doctors, investors (not speculators), pilots and so on. The professinals in these fields have generally a large skin in the game (money, reputation, their own life), making their advice worthy as compared to academic advise. The checklist book was then just the right fit for a lazy afternoon reading at once.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>